SCOTT FERNALD

Senior Software Engineer

+1 (770) 872 7817 • scott.fernald1110@gmail.com • scottfernald.netlify.app • Clearwater, FL

Summary

Persistent professional equipped with 13+ years of comprehensive experience in the Software Development industry. Provides strong technical direction across multiple projects. Experienced with the full software development lifecycle from planning to launch. Responsible and articulate individual with strengths in delivering high-quality software solutions and staying updated with industry trends. A big fan of basketball and karaoke. A self-motivated, avid learner.

Education

New College of Florida

B.S. in Computer Science

2007 - 2011

Experience

Fortunes Tech Goffstown, NH

Senior Software Engineer

01/2022 - Present

- Mentored and provided technical guidance to an engineering team of 10+ members.
- Spearheaded the transition of online meeting platform from PHP, DailyJS old stack into modern Angular, Python Flask, and LiveKit-based architecture, resulting in a remarkable 300% increase of client company's revenue.
- Implemented high-performance RESTful API endpoints using **Node.js** and **Nest** Framework.
- Designed Postgres database for microservices and optimized its performance by implementing advanced indexing strategies and query optimization.
- Led and participated in the development of various web and mobile applications including Renude, Relik and Droneblocks using cutting-edge technologies, including **Angular**, **React**, **React**, **Native**, **Next.js**, **Node.js**, **Golang**, **Python**, and **Laravel**.
- Actively contributed to code reviews, ensuring code quality, maintainability, and adherence to best practices.
- Strong background in cloud computing, including **AWS**, **GCP**, **Docker** and **Kubernetes**, proficient in designing and implementing cloud architectures, deploying and managing applications.
- Worked on CI/CD tools like **Jenkins** to automate the build process from version control tool into testing and production environment.

Velocity Global Denver, CO

Senior Software Engineer

05/2020 - 12/2021

- Served as one of the lead engineers in the development of Customer Experience Platform(CXP)-SaaS product of the company with a team of senior developers leveraging React, NextJS, Golang, GraphQL, Docker, and AWS.
- · Developed RESTful webservices and microservices using Golang for reading large volume of data from Postgres database.
- Laid and designed architectural foundation of **GraphQL** layers for transport route optimization and billing automate.
- Built a semi-auto mechanism which synchronously migrates CXP database into Glean data source using React, Node, Python and Glean
 APIs, resulting in a 30% improvement in speed and accuracy of data searching.
- Participated in the development of Document Management Platform(DOCX), providing **AWS Lambda**, **FormKiQ** and **OPA** solutions, and building high-performance RESTful APIs using **TypeScript** and **NodeJS**, handling an average of 1,000 large-scale requests per hour.
- Collaborated with staff and principal engineers to provide **proof of concept**, **TDD**, and design and develop robust solutions to meet product requirements.
- · Mentored less experienced team members to follow the advanced development principles and methods.

Sutherland Pittsford, NY

Software Engineer

01/2018 - 02/2020

- Collaborated with design team to create a **custom JavaScript UI framework** used across the company's internal projects, which improved development efficiency by 30% and ensured consistent branding and UI across the application.
- Led the end-to-end development process, including database design, frontend and back-end development, and **AWS deployment**, utilizing **Node**, **Angular**, **React**, **React Native** and **MongoDB** as the tech stack.
- Overcame the challenge of limited payment integration options in Malaysia by conducting extensive research and selecting the best available service.
- Successfully delivered the MVP within a tight timeframe of just 6 months, ensuring its successful adoption by customers who are actively
 utilizing the platform's car and motorcycle lending services.
- Developed BOTs for car renting and property management services using Chatfuel, Facebook, and Dialogflow BOT frameworks for Facebook Messenger.
- · Worked on managing the Git workflow, reviewing the completed tasks and conducting the code reviews.

Enumerate Clearwater, FL

Software Engineer

09/2016 - 11/2017

- Worked with a team of developers to migrate the existing UI from AngularJS to React, adding an extensive list of new features, unit tests
 and e2e tests for all features, key users, and roles.
- Implemented microservice architecture to upgrade efficiency of CRM system by 40%.
- Integrated a third-party identity service, **OKTA**, and related UI flows, including account activation, login, forgot password, and session management using JWT, token validation, and session cookies.
- · Assisted in enhancing the schema for a **RESTful API** to optimize its consumption by **Apollo Client**.
- Revamped the entire components and pages following the new Figma designs.
- Supported the CTO with various management tasks as high-level architectural decisions.

Enumerate Clearwater, FL

Front End Engineer

03/2014 - 09/2016

- Spearheaded the frontend development of ecommerce web applications using React, Redux, Typescript, MUI, Bootstrap, SCSS, etc.
- Refactored the client-side of applications into a reliable SPA architecture.
- · Provided seamless user interface, kanban board, data visualizations, and designed overall user experience.
- · Wrote high-quality code which covered 100+ unit and e2e tests to verify the functionality of UI components and overall workflow.
- · Stayed updated with the latest React and React Native trends and libraries to enhance the app's competitive edge.
- Provided powerful support to senior developers after becoming proficient in React and frontend technologies, resulting in a stronger, more
 efficient tech team.

TPGi Clearwater, FL

Software Engineer

05/2011 - 02/2014

- Developed the performance analytic tools utilizing PHP frameworks with senior developers, and focused on standard workflow & best practices.
- Learnt efficient work culture including **Git** and **Agile** methodologies
- Increased site traffic by providing user-oriented visuals and features using programming languages, including JavaScript and PHP.
- Utilized tools like **LESS** and **SASS** for CSS development.
- Developed **iOS** & **android** mobile applications from scratch to deploy.
- Participated in the bootcamp sessions to learn and implement JavaScript and PHP framework basis.

Skills

 $\textbf{Client-side}; \textbf{Angular} \cdot \textbf{React} \cdot \textbf{React} \cdot \textbf{Native} \cdot \textbf{Next.js} \cdot \textbf{VueJS} \cdot \textbf{Redux} \cdot \textbf{SCSS} \cdot \textbf{Material} \cdot \textbf{UI} \cdot \textbf{Tailwind} \cdot \textbf{CSS} \cdot \textbf{Storybook} \cdot \textbf{Jest} \cdot \textbf{Cypress}$

 $\underline{\mathsf{Server}\text{-}\mathsf{side}}; \mathsf{Node}. \mathsf{js} \cdot \mathsf{ExpressJS} \cdot \mathsf{NestJS} \cdot \mathsf{Golang} \cdot \mathsf{Python} \cdot \mathsf{Laravel} \cdot \mathsf{MySQL} \cdot \mathsf{PostgreSQL} \cdot \mathsf{Elasticsearch} \cdot \mathsf{GraphQL} \cdot \mathsf{MongoDB}$

 ${\color{red} \textbf{DevOps:}} \ \textbf{Docker} \cdot \textbf{Kubernetes} \cdot \textbf{Azure} \cdot \textbf{AWS} \cdot \textbf{Google Cloud Platform}$

Certification

React Expert Certificate — Hackerrank

AWS Certified Solutions Architect — Testdome

Backend Developer Certificate — Triplebyte

Freelancing



Freelance Full Stack Developer

04/2017 - 10/2020

Upwork